{
  "reference_number": "11866",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "Waiting for the commission will take too long I fear, even though they may have good advice. It is best that deadlines are set now and\n\n we are then under pressure to reach them rather than forever delaying until we find the 'perfect' solution everyone agrees on. This\n should never mean of course, that corners are cut or that marginalised sectors of society are made to carry the weight."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "The so-called 'short-lived' gases have a far greater effect despite being shorter-lived, especially given we are looking at a short time-\n frame to be able to turn back runaway climate chaos. Fugitive gas is particularly bad because we are wasting a really precious\n\n resource. Nitrous oxide from methane-based urea is poisoning and polluting soils, waterways and reefs which are crucial for\n sustainable economies and carbon capture. So reducing these products would have multiple benefits."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "One of the failures of the ETS was allowing international carbon markets that achieved very little other than driving the carbon price\n\n down and aiding corrupt business. If we focus on domestics markets it will be much more sustainable and increase a local carbon\n economy that creates much needed jobs, especially in rural areas."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But only if to make it sooner rather than later. We need to expect that there will be many emergencies in the near future because of\n climate change and demands on global resources and therefore plan emergencies into the strategy not use them as excuses to exit\n\n the strategy."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "Again this should only be to make it better not worse as in speed up the process not slow it down"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "As said previously, there are enough predictions already about the increasing number of emergencies we will face. This needs to be\nworked into strategies at the beginning"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But there is too much focus on business and fuel supply. There needs to be a really strong focus on sustainable economies as in\nlocal, decentralised infrastructure for transport, trade, education, health, recreation. There needs to be an understanding of\n\necological sustainability for new or old technologies such as regenerative agriculture, rongoā, biological farming, freshwater\nindigenous fisheries and textile industries... Access for support must be fair"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Of course or how else will we achieve these goals."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Those most affected must have more say, especially the young, the poor, women and tāngata whenua. They should also have more\ninput into solutions as typically their solutions are more economically and socially sustainable since they focus on need, using what\n\nthey have be it low or no budgets or humble experts with generations of local knowledge. It would be wrong and stupid to look for\nsolutions from the same capitalist models and fossil fuel industries who got us into this mess."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "However I don't see why we should be using international emissions reductions to fulfill our targets. This should be removed from the\n\nlist."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "I would prefer experts over politicians but it depends of course on what experts on what subjects and under what process eg. does\nthe chair get veto rights? And who chooses the experts? Whoever is chosen needs to be unconflicted by financial, political or social\nprejudice."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I would add knowledge of sustainable development techniques and planning in particular energy, agriculture, housing, trade and\n\ntransport"
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But this should not override the focus of preventing climate change. Some adaption is needed urgently such as plant resilience and\n\nreducing flood and drought effects."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It would be good to see this extended to the private sector as well such as large industries like Fonterra and power companies that, if\n\nthey topple, will have major effects on our people"
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I am happy to see a bill like this finally being drafted and I really hope it comes out strong. It would be foolhardy if decision-makers on\n\nthis bill were swayed by the interests of the rich and powerful. We have looked after the interests of a few over the interests of the\n99% for far too long. Please do the right thing.\n\n\n\n\n You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
